so
i was wanting to talk about
uh emotions
you know
are emotions
good or bad
are they
is there something wrong with them
should they be cultivated
or should they be avoided
well how can you cultivate how can you
avoid it
well you could
give in to your emotions you know every
little emotion you feel you could
express it and act out of it and it um
you know just run with the kind of thing
you feel a sense of love so you start
hugging everyone telling how much
telling everyone how much you love what
you feel right yeah
you get angry
just get angry you know
punch someone in the face hey hey enjoy
uh
so i mean i asked that question but i i
know i know they aren't saying you know
eye emotions good or bad well
some emotions
people will say are are good and other
emotions are bad
but our emotions
the world of emotions is it a good thing
or a bad thing
exactly so so you have emotions that are
good and emotion that are bad
but being liable to emotions that's not
good fundamentally
fundamentally
existentially that is a problem
so liability to emotions
is an issue
because uh
well there you go you are liable
to these waves that are
not in your control that are sometimes
good and sometimes bad
which means either way they have to be
endured which means either way you are
under the pressure of them
so it's not good
that's not to say also all emotions in
terms of the content are bad no they're
good emotions nice emotions and bad
emotions like unwholesome emotions
but fundamentally the nature of emotion
is a problem because
well it puts you in that
perilous
position uh which which is
being subjected to
you know feelings
exactly that's fundamentally what the
problem is like um
people tend to not think about the
feelings or emotions when those are good
or where those are not too threatening
or not too um
not reminding you know not dangerous and
so on um
but those things change
uh you you can get some some feelings
they will be revealing the
the danger the unpleasantness and that
you don't know the escape from it
and then and then you realize ah feeling
is the problem
you wouldn't be in the position
of um
kind of
pinned down by an unpleasant feeling of
something that happened that you don't
know how to escape from
if you haven't been cultivating
gratuitous ownership
appropriation and carelessness in regard
to the feeling per se
and that
that unwholesome type of cultivation
happens basically through
um just you know accepting the pleasant
feeling taking it for granted
and and assuming that you can always
outrun the unpleasant feeling but
you don't realize that either way you're
deeply bound with a feeling
which is not in your control
so it's like that similarly i gave
before i think i don't even record it or
maybe just some of the talks
you know like you you
you basically you find yourself like
riding a horse
that you can't get off of you you can't
come down from it
and [Music]
[Music]
he doesn't listen to you really
so it goes where he wants to go
and when those things
that he wants to see
are nice and agreeable you enjoy the
ride but then sometimes something else
takes its fancy and he goes wild and
runs to the sort of you know
uh
thorny bushes and in cliffs and in
rough stones and you fall off and then
you're dragged and so and then you
realize okay so riding a horse is a
dangerous experience because i'm not in
the control of a horse
so i can pretend everything is fine when
the horse is sort of
just you know taking a a slow stride
along the beach or something it's very
pleasant and easy
but then when it's galloping through
some some wild woodland and i'm getting
cut up and beaten
uh oh that's a problem but you don't
want to wait for that you want to start
training the horse before
it gets into the you know
areas and positions they will harm you
well it's the same with your mind and
same with the feelings so if you're only
if you're enjoying the presence of your
mind and your thoughts and the life
when feelings are good
you are making yourself liable to then
equally suffer when those feelings
change and that's it you don't need to
and that's it you don't need to
experience bad feelings by the way
just not having enough of the good
feelings that you had is already felt
badly it's already felt
unpleasantly so because of your dependence on good
so because of your dependence on good
emotions and good feelings in good moods
you become even more sensitive more
liable to the bad ones
because what is bad is relative from
that point of view
not having enough of a pleasant emotion
is unpleasant
but if you were not so dependent on the
unpleasant emotions sorry if you were
not so dependent on the pleasant
emotions uh you wouldn't be so quick basically to
uh you wouldn't be so quick basically to
fall into that resistance of the
unpleasant ones because the mind
wouldn't move because the mind is not
that dependent
so that's what i mean it kind of depends
on emotions and feelings not that you
can't not that you can stop them but you can
not that you can stop them but you can
certainly
uh not appropriate them whereas the
buddha would say not welcome them not
delighting them not not lose perspective
in regard to them and that's that's what
you want to do
so you want to be creating
a broader context in regard to whatever
you're feeling here and now that's
enduring so you're not trying to get rid of it
so you're not trying to get rid of it
and you're certainly not trying to
indulge it and you're certainly not
trying to explain it and psychologize it
all you're trying to do is remain
unmoved by it
and you do so by developing the full
understanding of that context that you
know that fundamentally they are
unownable they come on their own like
the waves and that you are the one who
chooses to jump into them
and then get all wet and soaked and so
on so
so
so then so someone might say well
you know i love
i love love i love happiness
i i love excitement and that passionate
uh
drive adventure and all that
those exciting emotions
and and then they they strive they strive
and then they they strive they strive
just to have that
you know and and
and focus just on that part
so
is there a way just to have those
pleasant feelings
feelings
is focusing on just
the that uh that possibility of pleasant
emotions a good thing
a good thing
you know so is it possible just to have
pleasant emotions first of all
emotions first of all
is it possible just to have that
yeah so the whole the whole thing is uh if
so the whole the whole thing is uh if
somebody wants to focus on that yeah
that's fine
they will experience that degree of
happiness that degree of central joy to
that extent for that amount of time
um
but then
and if that's their choice yeah that's
fine there's nothing like
uh morally wrong with it unless of
course their actions are harming others
and so on
um but uh universally speaking from the
point of view of a human experience that
is liable to certain things
that same person if they were to have
some wisdom or if they're interested in
developing wisdom should ask themselves
okay well what are the prerequisites for
me
being able to focus only on pleasant
experiences chase them get as much as i
want enjoy the life enjoy sensuality
what are the necessary conditions for
that well being alive is the first condition
well being alive is the first condition
being healthy is the second condition
having functioning senses is the third
condition so
so
pretty much you know having having
strength in zeal is is the condition so
then am i in control of those conditions that
am i in control of those conditions that
are necessary
for me to be able to chase the happiness
and enjoy it
and that thought enough will be that
thought will be enough to to you know
reveal the anxiety underneath whereby
sure you can chase the pleasures if you want
you can chase the pleasures if you want
by ignoring the nature of your situation
that you are not in control of that
horse that is liable to sickness aging
and death and it will take you basically
when it goes
so
your happiness that you're getting on
account of that basis
is very limited very perilous and very
intoxicating in a sense of
uh it makes you forget
the true nature of your situation that
you could die at any given moment that
you could get sick and give a moment
that your senses will fail i mean can
you enjoy the beautiful sight sound
smell taste touches if you can't see
hear smell taste to touch
impossible and that is like what that is that is
and that is like what that is that is
the the kind of the most frightening
idea a person would have imagine you you
get into that um how's it called
medically like a locked in syndrome you
know where basically you're alive inside
but your senses everything is just shut
out so you have no perception of the
so you have no perception of the
external world yet you are aware of
yourself that is basically a situation at any
that is basically a situation at any
given time
that is what existence is
it's just that these uh
external sense objects you know being
inducive of lust and you taking them for
granted and seeking them further outside
makes you basically forget that makes
you forget your current situation that
you're always fully enclosed within
yourself and there is no way out
certainly not in that
external sense that you would be seeking
so
from that universal point of view yes
it's not good then to be blind like that
and just intoxicated and infatuated with
the current pleasures and happiness and
emotions you're feeling because it masks
the the real nature of your situation
but from your individual point of view
if that's what you want to do yeah
that's fine you'll get the results
and uh and you'll pay the price one way
or the other
and also as you say you know you are not
control or in control of your senses
your body you know you get diseases and
so on
or your wealth and so on but yeah the
external things that you are
dependent upon say for example your
children you know so you you love seeing hearing
you know so you you love seeing hearing
experiencing your children you know
watching them grow up
and it's and it's such a wonderful
experience the birth and
the way they start learning about things
and it's they're so cute and it's
fascinating uh and you're just overflowing with joy
uh and you're just overflowing with joy
and love and then
yeah they get cancer or someone hits
them you know have an accident on the road
you know have an accident on the road
hits them with a car
and now
you're so dependent on that thing out
there so far away from your your body
which you are not even in control of let alone
you are not even in control of let alone
another person's body
and you've spilled out so far
so emotionally dependent when that thing
changes in a horrible way or you know just in a
in a horrible way or you know just in a
simple way that's disagreeable to you in
some even a small way
you're completely shattered
you know your life is um
well yeah because you've been you've
been riding really really high up you've
been high up
and now that thing came crashing and you
didn't have time to come down safely
there's that dependence on family and
children and possessions and wealth
and things that are even more removed
out of your control so
so
so then you know if you if you're
speaking to a person who who is
uh dependent on those external things
very emotionally
uh dependent
and you know you know it is a wonderful
thing to love your children to be kind
to them and you know
but there is that danger there
so
that's the reality of it um
so like people will often then kind of
jump into conclusion that ah so it's
dangerous so you're saying it's bad to
love children
it's as i said it's not a moral question
it's from the universal point of view of
your situation
what is basically um
skillful what is unskillful
well it's unskillful to live on top of a
tree that somebody's cutting and you
refuse to come down
that is unskillful but you're still free
to do so
but you will be responsible for
everything that happens to you
um so so again the choices on the the
choices on the person
uh and if
you know if they don't absolutely know
any other way
to live
any any form of withdrawal of sense of
strength well the most you can do is encourage
well the most you can do is encourage
them at least to be virtuous within that
parallel situation
but if a person does want to practice
and is familiar with the dharma
and is in that position of depending on
external circumstances to a great extent
well then yeah you might just want to
remind them of the the the implicit
peril and the sense of urgency that's
right there visible to them
because that's that having a perspective
on that thing that you
love you know having aspect of that yes
you know having aspect of that yes
things could
you know you could experience good
things you know pleasant feelings so to
speak but you can equally experience
painful feelings things can be going
quite well for you and then all of a
sudden you know you get a disease there's an
you know you get a disease there's an
accident there's a murder those things
happen in the world so you can focus on
all the positive things in the world all
the lovely things
the adventures you can have the
excitement the new discoveries and so on
but if you just see that part of the world
if you just see that part of the world
you are narrow-minded in that in that
sense and then when the other part
affects you you are going to be uh
you know surprised in a horrific kind of
way you're going to be well that's that's
you're going to be well that's that's
the thing like a person can also then
choose to just be focused on the
negative and um
and um
and equally lose perspective
uh the point is to find the middle
ground and then you will feel
responsibility on account of it and the
weight of your actions and you will
choose much more wisely
even as i said even without needing to
renounce the whole world and become a
monk and so on
so if if if you basically through your
own reflection c
that yes you kind of don't like to think
about you know what is of the negative
kind you only like to focus on the
positive well that's why you should
think about the negatives
and the what-ifs
um
not oh i must like you know get rid of
my children and everything else no but i
must broaden the context and prevent
that narrowing of my mind to occur on
account of being absorbed and taking
this pleasure for granted
and equally if all you're doing
is just seeing the negative and thinking
about the murders and accidents and so
on
you could equally lose perspective then
and recognize yeah but that's not
happening all the time
it's it's not that life is all about
that either
so from that point of view you could
then kind of you know broaden that
narrowness by actually thinking on the
good side on the you know there is
friendship in the world there is
kindness there is wholesome there is
virtue there are results of good actions
and then basically keep the balance
uh learn how to stay in the middle
regardless of what your tendency is
whether to just focus on the positive
and ignore the negative or just to dwell
and wallow in negative and and just
dismiss and and be cynical in regards to
any positive
so if you are actually sustaining that
balance then yes as i said your actions
will feel differently the weight behind
them will feel differently and you your
joy on account of children or misery in
a kind of world will be something you
will feel
uh responsible in other words you will
know you're responsible for that state
of mind
so you won't be projecting the
the fault onto the world
nor would you be projecting the the old
happiness just comes from the world then
all i need to do is protect it now you
would see that he comes from your state
of mind where he chooses basically and
how he chooses to attend things and
and
and i was i was
i was thinking about you know that so
you have people who
just uh
go with their emotions no restraint
no restraint
no perspective and then
you have also this uh
this kind of
emotion of indifference you know
uh
crushing crushing your feelings so to be
keeping them locked away
you feel them
but you you keep them subdued you know
like a like a soldier
or a warrior
the stoic indifference stoic
indifference you know
managing your emotions not letting them
get out of hand so overpowering them
out of hand so overpowering them
so you are
you are experiencing pleasure you're
experiencing a heightened you know state
of
uh
emotion but you control yourself you
restrain yourself
and you just get the job done whatever
you want you need to do in your life you
just get it done you uh
you overpower your emotions you kind of
ignore them in a way
well you know
which is strange you don't you can't
really ignore them to ignore them you need to
ignore them to ignore them you need to
know that they are there
and so you're kind of suppressing them
that's what i want to say you're kind of
suppressing them
and then you get this person who's like
the stoic
indifferent soldier
warrior you know shoot some kill people
and don't try not to feel what it feels
like right well the original stoicism was
right well the original stoicism was
about but yeah i think people might
think that's what it is just to repress
your feelings and sort of
well that's that's the other way you're
just trying to try to deny the reality
the existence of the fact that you are
still feeling it's not
so you're not being genuinely unmoved by
feeling because you understood the
unknown ability on account of your
virtues and skillful behavior developed
beforehand no you're just trying to cover up the
no you're just trying to cover up the
fact that you are still liable but you
just try to take even further control
and basically kind of
cement it all with your attitude no i
don't feel anything but that that cannot
be sustained either see that attitude is
also dependent on the same things that
your feelings and your joys depend on
it depends on the circumstances it
depends on your determination it depends
on your intention your health it depends
on the current set of circumstances that
are not too challenging so that you can
sustain the determination to not feel
anything and overpower everything else
but when things change
uh again when the health goes senses
start to fail you start being
overwhelmed from all sides even that
intention will go so it has a limited it
has a basically um
it has its own shelf life
so yeah so again so there is
the gratification in emotions there are
gratification in emotions there are
pleasant emotions you know
there is the danger
of emotions you know being
you you're just moved by them you're
making decisions upon them whatever you
feel that's why you act
and so on so there's that danger
so
how not to be moved by emotions how
how how to escape them so
how to escape them so
you will be able to not be moved by
emotions which are on the level of your
mind if you have sufficiently practiced um
if you have sufficiently practiced um
not being moved by all the things to the
kind of uh the results of it
so if you stopped acting
carelessly without perspective
unwholesomely uh with your body
and sustain that as your day-to-day
living that perspective of certain
non-action you know the aggregate of
virtue we spoke about
equally if you if you have ceased all
the unwholesome actions actions by
speech they were rooted in in all these
other like subtly movements due to
emotions and so on
and then eventually you'll be able to
equally remain unmoved and not act out
of the mental state of whatever you're
currently feeling
but you cannot live your life
the way it is which is undermined life
undermined and controlled by influenced
by emotions and somehow magically expect
to just be able to pull the emotion part
out without everything else changing
that's that's like putting pulling the
bottom uh the you know like a house of cards
uh the you know like a house of cards
pulling the bottom card out and
expecting the the whole kind of creation
to remain standing that's not possible
because everything is rooted in how you
feel
so that's why it's not like i must stop
doing everything because that's another
doing thus it's impossible to accomplish
stop not doing of everything
but you can
direct your doing in the in the
direction they will tame your mind
uh reduce the dependence of of you on
your emotions and pleasures
so it's not about killing the horse and
strangling it while you're riding it
because you come crashing with it it's
about training it it's about not going
where you know you shouldn't be going
and developing that strength and ability
of sense restraint and then sustaining
it
so it's it's there is no other like um
people might assume how this so some
great magical revelation will come out
of my sense restraint no sense restraint
will come out of the sense restraint
and once you start seeing that you see a
direct link then to how you develop and
train that horse ah like this by
preventing it from doing things you
shouldn't be doing by making you do
things that it doesn't want to do but we
both know are good for it
so basically again skillful reflection
skillful behavior precepts and
sustaining mindfulness on account of
those actions throughout the day
that is what you should do
and you will know that that in itself is
already a benefit
that is already a reward
and when the mind settles when the whole
settles into that then you get even a
higher reward
now you are the one riding and controlling
you are the one riding and controlling
the horse and telling you where to go
it it cannot drag you into the thorny
bushes where you're gonna get strangled
and you know with your head knocked off
and so on
because you're in charge but it goes and
it listens to you now
and that is true pleasant abiding here
and now
and that takes to be developed so
so
there is there is a state of mind
that can be developed that is
that can last you can say last forever
for as long as you're alive
well yeah that yeah
so and that is what you in a way that's
what you're talking about that states of
peace exactly a state of wholesome peace
and obviously you know
as i said depending on how much
well it depends how much you allow that
horse to still engage with its wild
desires to that extent you can expect
kind of the the corresponding piece so
if you don't allow it as much
you can have a greater piece if you
still let it run wild every now and then
well to that extent you are diminishing
your possibility of peace but
still any effort you make towards taming
it will result to that degree of peace
so it's it's never it's never going to
go to waste
because that is ultimately what
everybody wants i mean the reason people
become infatuated with the you know
pleasant experiences of the horse riding
in this simile is because of the
peaceful pleasure that they get from it
the satisfying the gratification
basically gratification results in peace
resulting in temporary calmness of
subsiding of your desires
obviously you arrived at them through
violent scratching of the itch
so it's going to come back even worse
because of that but fundamentally even
pursuit of the desires and the pleasures
and sensuality is done with the peace as
the ultimate result of it so
even if you don't want to be sense
restraint if you don't want peace of
this kind you actually still want peace
if you look deep down
the the end project of all the you know
desires and gains and and possessions
and joys and emotions that people have
is that peaceful pleasure
oh nice that's why also people would
then come immediately jump into
conclusion into assumption that oh wow
this is so nice and immediately assume
that it will last forever
because it's just too nice to think that
he won't
so that whole notion of eternal and
permanent is not some like a you know a
philosophical glitch in your mind no
it's the result of your emotional
dependence and pleasure you naturally
assume that this will never change
because just thinking that it might
change undermines that peace of that
pleasure so whether you admit it to yourself or
so whether you admit it to yourself or
not you want peace
it's just what you do
in order to get it it's how you choose
to go about it that's what's going to
determine whether you're going to get it
or not and whether you're going to pay
price for it or not
so so when i
that kind of that kind of peace actual
peace you know being unmoved by
you know being unmoved by
uh pleasant feeling
being unmoved by
unpleasant feeling
that that kind of that the peace to that
extent that you're still actually having
that you're still actually having
pleasant feelings and
unpleasant feelings
but you're unmoved by them
that peace is kind of horrifying for
people when i
explain to them
that kind of piece is absolutely
horrifying it's like that's because even
even even the piece that they know they
have no understanding of it
you know if they were to actually
develop at least some basic wisdom in
regard to their own situation
without you know
giving things up and so on and enduring
they would they would well it would be
easy for them to come come to terms with
it but
they're so unaware
that any notion of of that kind of
stilling and uh and what you will be describing
and uh and what you will be describing
is peaceful it just feels like oh that
means i'm dead
yeah it's death
it's death
it is death that's people in the suttas
who were scared when the buddha would
describe nibana
what else is there other than you know
if you're not feeling something you're
dead uh if you'd or you you know you're alive
uh if you'd or you you know you're alive
but you're kind of it means they're so
unaware even of the nature of their feelings
even of the nature of their feelings
they don't even see that they often
don't feel anything and yet they're not
dead they just don't see it that's what it
they just don't see it that's what it
would have meant the neutral feeling is
completely unseen not understood and
that's why it's felt unpleasantly
but if you see it and understand it it
will actually feel pleasantly
so yeah
the only reason they can even
the only reason they can even be scared
or horrified by the idea of peace is
because deep down they recognize what
that neutral feeling is
means they know it they just refuse to
admit it to themselves
because of the dependence on that
exactly exactly the pleasure the
dependence on that kind of movement
activity happening engagement
it's the only way
you know a person knows how to
uh
escape or relieve themselves
well that's what i said you know
like it's it's it's kind of relative you
don't start
as soon as you're born
by that high dependence on on a pleasant
activity and engagement and so on you
develop it carelessly
so that's why people who are super
hyperactive always engaged even but
they're slightly less engaged still very
much engaged but slightly less engaged
mind will be filled with boredom and
dread and because not enough is
happening because their minds became
even more dependent
on even higher level and there is no end
to that it is like an addiction the more
you take the more you'll need to take
you know not getting
emotional is a sign that you know you are handling
is a sign that you know you are handling
your feelings well um
well um
it depends i suppose i mean i know what
you mean but if somebody hears it like
that means okay so i must just prevent
means okay so i must just prevent
emotions from happening and that's how
i'm handling my feelings no
you must not be acting out of your
emotions so that's how you're handling
your feelings
so you're able to let them arise
to the extent they want to arise
either way you won't be moved by it
that's how you're handling your feelings
because yeah managing your feelings
managing your emotions is still
management you're still you're still
having
acting out of it yeah you're overwhelmed
by an emotion thus you are needing to
handle it
whatever you're feeling whatever
emotions are pressuring you
you have the threshold of the virtue of
the precepts that's your container
within that
you focus on not losing perspective in a
situation for as long as the emotion
lasts and not giving in to the pressure to act
and not giving in to the pressure to act
out of it
so it's not going to be perfect in the
beginning you will be
still doing it to some extent out of
desire to manage it get rid of it but if
these sort of um
frameworks are protected
um
that motivation will subside and you'll
start doing it more and more rightly
right it's like that um as you're saying
before so you you you
handle your emotions don't act out of
them you know you know
um
you can then gain a restraint and so on
you gain a perspective on your feelings
which means you can start understanding
their nature
what the fundamental nature of feelings
are and thus be free from them so when
and thus be free from them so when
no matter how intense they uh come
manifest yeah yeah at that point you you would be
yeah yeah at that point you you would be
able to start seeing that
freedom from feeling is not freedom from
um
feelings arising it's freedom from
basically you owning them you cannot own them now
you owning them you cannot own them now
even if you want to
they're truly seen as impersonal as in
things out there in the world that come
and go
so they cannot move you because it's not
yours not your problem and that's truly
not felt